All right, we'll call it to order the records. We got a meeting in Moments City Council for Monday March 20th 2023
The Proclamation declaring March 13th 2020-23 tomorrow morning's 19th 2021 as brain awareness week motion
Number 3 proclamation declaring march 28
The next week, January 20th 2023 is Chuck Stopts appreciation day. I want to say something too on the tell-in
To this course a lot of you know that chuck passed away and Chuck was
A leader in our community
And he led by example
People saw it
And I had a gentleman call me little over week we can have to go and said,
Wanted tell you something about Chuck Stopts. He says in 2007 my house flooded
He said it was just me and my son, 16 year old Son.
I'm a single dad trying to work take care of him on his own
And he says we got flooded
We didn't know what would tell you about this
We were out our house
We didn't have a lot of money and we were trying to clean up
He said I knew he had given our cleanup. So,
And when the wall marked me
When i got in there
The stuff on either that couldn t afford
My son is standing here
And i don t have the money to clean his house and give him a home to stay in
He said about that time this guy walked up
This guy was 7 foot tall
I mean he says, what's going on?
What can do it help you
Emotionally upset but actually couldn't talk today
He said, my 16 year old son
Explain to him what our situation was and we had been flooded
And then trying clean up house
We didn t have the money
To buy everything he needed
This 7 foot guy grabbed a cart
Then it says come on follow me
They went down an aisle by all
Chuck put stuff in his car cleaning supplies
Gloves boots mobs
Everything that they need
He told him i don t have the money to pay for this
And he said, I do and
Said what?
One of these days
Pay it forward someone else
So many times its crazy but every time
I paid up over thinking about Chuck
What did you say from me in my son
That s a guy who got out chucked off
He led by example
So it s an honor for me today
I don t want to speak with these guys
But i m sure they re honored as well
The name March 28 which is Chuck's birthday
As Chuck Stots Day in my home
Im all calm
Um, im talking about Walmart
And on March 28 you can go into WalMart
Everybody has an MCAPK
They are going get a cup of k-sought
To celebrate Chuck stot day
They also have donated
Two hundred dollar gift tickets
To lind these organization
For her to help raise money for
Her organizations that i know are deadloves
So um, guys we re going
Take a picture in March 28
Can be Chuck Stots Day and I no he would probably laugh at us right now
And name it day after him
But i feel like
He deserves more than anybody
Mayor before you do they
Just want to also go into
And then they are dead
Um, okay we re going do 13
While were here
13 is a resolution
CC 2020-06
Name the intersection of WalMart
First Christian Church
Which many you know that first Christian church was Chuck's first door
We ve been name
And then we came into that intersection
Into the parking lots
That Main Street has Chuck Stots Way
If you get a motion and approval here
I never told him, You guys see
See how street sign
Just tell what Chuck stot s way was
Then thats paying up for it
Take care everybody else
So every time he sees
Sons says Chuck's thoughts away
Thank y'all
And number 4
Proclamation declaring April 2023
As autism awareness
An acceptance month
I'll make a motion to approve
Okay
One more
It's maybe
Because of us or because you re former, she coming out
Five public input
You get a personal appearances
Six consent agenda
Staff recommends we approve about him seven and eight
Here y'all
Number 9
Performed representation by Crawford & Associates
I really mean you i thought all this people were here to listen
To the accounting
So thankyou Mayor
And members of The Council
Give me just few minutes
Talk About Everybody's Favorite Topic Accounting
Every year I'll show up once a year and give an update of the financial health
And performance at The City for last years
Here with good news tonight
On No Last Month, he auditor was here
Went through this 95 page
Document maybe you didn't go to it all hopefully that would be painful
But one thing they oughta doesn t do
It tells y'all numbers are right but i didnt tell ya what number is mean
Weve been doing This Performer
For 20 plus Years To Try to Explain ToThe city
I ask you on a scale of zero to ten how are we doing
Could You Answer That?
With Ten Being Excellent Financial Health and Success
And A Zero Being Poor Financial health & Success
Weve done that,
But do it analytically every year
In fact i have 11 international governments
If y'all flip the page five
All explain To The results Of This Year
Picka handfuls lives to kind go through
And let's see it like in
So if y'all notice your score for the year 8.4
That is probably one of The top three or four scores
Not only Inthe State Of Oklahoma this Year but Probably AcrossThe Country
This model has designed where there isn't a government that could score at ten
across every ratio so,
Ten Government doesn t exist, nor does zero
Although Puerto Rico Is Testing My Zero
Theory
Thank you
So, You have Hovered Around The Low 8s
Loatimate Eight's Last Two Years That s really good
Most people will flash into the eightes maybe once
And then come back down Into The Mid-Sevens
Y'all Been Hovering InThe Age for Three years Now and Historically Ive been in
High or Seven Or Aates
This score didn t change a whole lot from this year
To last Year we introduced it to Tad
But again the High Score AcrossThe Country In 23 years has been a 9.1
It t only happened twice in 23 Years
One Government Oklahoma and then one in Georgia
So 8.4 is extremely good
The overall health picture of A8 .04 can actually be
Divided up into three categories, it s not really just help
Its Health Performance & Sustainability
Ican Really assigna score to eachone Of Those Components
So when you look to the right at The Top
You see that this word called Financial Position
That s really Health Score
Physician & health means same thing
Your scoring in Mid-Mid To Lower Sixes
At Both Years Again 5 is Satisfactory
So financial health Is Improving
It's improving because of Performance
For Last Three years we have been scoring a 10 on all five or six
Rations Related to performance Meaning
12 month Year to year in Performance for That fiscal year
Has been very good
Sustainability or Capabilities scores and 8.3
This year that s excellent
Also, thats means basically you control quite a bit of your revenue stream
You got low debt per capita burden
Low tax per capital burdens
And have the ability To sustain this operation
Overalong period
There s a lot of you stay above the five
Theres about 17 different ratios that kind
Of going into these equations I m not gonna hit everyone
Im just pick up couple them to highlight
And then maybe let yass some questions
Stride your pants
Probably The first one i am in Apututus on page 9
Which is what im calling unessigned
Fun Balance On General Fund
Here are You Score Just About Satisfactory
And I m going to say that you are going
What this is basically looks at the main fund of
The City where we run Most Of
The city operations through fire police, streets parks
Everything runs Through General Fund
Atthe end-of day
That has something what We call carry over or fun balance
As i like To see as we LikeTo See unassigned
Carrier Overat least equivalent
10% If You rebelled in streams
This year were 11%.
What this slide doesn t really show You in the graph
Over In The Narrative where we actually have If i were to count all of you
Signed To Fun Balance and Add it Into
An Assigned Fund balance As Simply Management Making
Decision that they want to spend That Money
We Have A Signed Fund Balance Of 3.6 million
So if HadThatToThe Million, thats Unassined
We have about 4.6 million of What i would call A
Available Money To Spend and That Would Generate About a 50%
Ration instead Of 11%.
So this year the City Basically said we re going to Take Some
This Excessive General Fund And were Going
Updug It Dispended In The Subsequent Year
Here, You are in Right Now
Again thats Not Bad Thing
Make sure that WE maintain Carrier Over Fun Balance Atat
And That For Cash Flow Purposes or One Time Emergencies
Of Things of At Nature
But Again, We have A Signed Or You Have a Sign Quite
Abit To Fun Balance to Be Used In The Subsequent Year
Next Two slides i think I will Flip 2
On page 14 and 15.
The deal with cash flow.
You score 10s on these
Are we going Give you an 11 but the Score won t go past
Basically were Measuring Whether Vinders & Employees
Or Police With Our Ability to Pay a Long Time
You know when Vinders & Employees Are Abilies
Have To Wait 2 Months to Get paid
If We had 6 months of Getting Paid
Or Do They get Paved Within 30 Days
Were Looking At How Much Money we have in Current Assets
Offset Every Current Live Billion that
So really For every Doll or Wio
were Hoping That Had at least $2
It's going Turn Into Cash
Very Quickly In Ordered Of Payit
We have got $3.83
So we are Well Above the 2-1 Ratio
On The Next slide,
Just pure Cash and say
DoWe Have At least 1 Doll or In cash
For Every One Dollar That Were Going To Have to Write Checks For
And Here
We Are Two Dollars & 72 Cent
Again Far More than What Is Required Cash Flow
So Again Good Cash Flows
And Then On The Slide 16
Is Kind Of A Summary of All the Financial Position
Or Health Ration Us.
Plus a 5 year Trend Analysis
As You Can See What This Score Has Been
Notice as far as To Help Score
If We Go Back At The Very Bottom
Discollete In First Column There on The Lift
We Were Below At 5 at The End of Discollete
And Now we're In the Mid Sixes
So,We've gotten Here.
But Because Of You Had Such Good Performance
For Last 3 or 4 Years That It's Making Us
Healthier From A Position Stand On
Next slide Off Probably 1-2 is
Beginning Over The Performance Slides
Which Is On Slide 19
We're Basically Measuring And Again There's 5
Performance Slides.
You Score To 10 on Every One Of It That'S Why
you Scored A10 On The Performance aspect
Basically What we are Looking Here Is
This is the Government Worth More At
End of Year Than what it Was at
Beginning In On Slide 19
It basically Says Yes,Were Worthmore Our Net Position
Are Networked Through By About 7 million
Which As about 16%
We Were Over In The City Side On the Government
Electivities And we Also grew on
Utility Side On Business Time.
So I'm Really Not Gonna Spend A Whole Lot of
Of These Five Slides That You Did so Well
Will Point To Slide 22
Measure Your Net Service Cover
Do Other Words?
Are Bond Investors Or People that were Taking Loans or
Signing Leases With,Are They Happy
Of The Ability of the Pay Them Back In
And To Now It Looks Like You Just Approved
Six Leases Participate That's Well
Welts State Bank, Whoever you awarded
Is Loaning Your This Money At Such A Great Great
Because They Know We Are Gonna Pay it Back
Really Have an Excellent Net Service Cover
we Only Look About 1.5 Times
An Annual Advertising Service in Year Generating
Nearly Five times
So If Our Work Credit Or Loaning your Money
I'd Be Pleased to be Loaning Your Money Also
The Last Slide In That Growth Or in the Performance
Side of Sales Tax I Don't Really Know How To Explain This
It's Just Crazy.
Usually, Sales tax Pre-COVID We Were Luck If
At State Stagnant or Maybe Group 1%
92 percent A Year that Would Be Great
Since COVID You Had Three Consective Years Of Growth
5.6%, 16.4%.
And Then For Physical 22 Another 8%
That's ridiculous.
It is Unheard of, it
Not Sustainable So If I'm Gonna Say Anything Bad
This Is Going To Come Down At Some Point
Although Based On What Im Seeing Through
Vibreory Of this Year
Its not Coming Down Yet Still A Head
Double Digital Growth Or The average
In Sales Tax Unless You Change the Rate
Is Usually On Heart Of Unless You Chock Some of This Up To Deplation
Because Everything Cost More Now
So The Flesh In Producers A Little More Sales Tax Also
But I Don't Think It Increases At this Level
Something Good Going On People Are Taking Their Local Money
They're Staying Locals, they are Bying local
If you Can Continue to Encourage That and Sustainless
The Better Off You'll Be.
Sales Tax Is One Of the Two Main Streams of Revenue
That you Live off Other When Being Utilities
So Thats Really Only 2 Things
They Have To Generate A Significant amount of Money
So Sales And Use Tax is Still On A Tear
Again We will Keep Watching that too
But thats Against Gord 10 on Growth
Flight 24, I see All Last 5 Years Of Performance
And We've Had Actually 5 Years Of Performance
3-10s in A Row Last 4 years
Then Even In The Years of 1819 we Scored a Night
So Again Thats What Raises Your Health
Every Year Is You Continue To Perform At your Best
From Up to Natural Conditions Staying Coming
Last That Assides Talk About Sustainability
Probably Just Go To the Summary Slide On Flight 33 Here
This Score Doesn't Change Very Much from Year 2
Notice It Kind Of Hover Is Around The High 7s or Low 8
What This is kind of Measuring As I mentioned earlier
Do We Control Some Revenue Stream To the Point Where If Something Were to Happened
On The Stream we Don't Control Can We Cover That
And Answer Yes, You Can Control About 74%
Our Debt Service Load Or How Much We're Paying
All our Expendateurs that Are Non Capital Related
How Much Of It Relates To Debt, Its Only 8.8%
That's Very Good Score Also
Thats Means We're Not Paying A lot of DET Service Out Our Angel Expendateurs
And Then You Have No Geo Bond Dead On Standing General Obligation Bond
That Requires a Voted People
But With Those Geobons you Can Do Things Like In Pistructure
Another Improvement If He can Get it Past
It Paced For itself With A Property Tax Levy That You Don't Have Access to Right Now
The City Doesn'T Let Be a Property Tax Only the Counties In This Schools
I Wether IfThe city Were To Issue Bond Dead On A $20 Million Road Project
Or Some Other Development Project
He Would Then be A Leverying Small Part Of Property Tax Every Year
Paying The Annual DET Service on that
Geobons Which You Don'T Have In By Issuing On That You Could Literally Pay For It Improvement
Assessing A Property Tax which you don't Do Right Now
So, IfYou have that Whole Capability
The whole Sustainability Open To Also Thats Why We Score So Well on the Sustainability
I Think i Took 15 minutes And Im About Like 30
Any Questions about How we Go About This or The End Resolter
Any particular slide you Want To Talk About Or More Than Happened?
We Do This Every Year So Im Just Kind Of A Simple Way to Get a Gage of Are we Healthy and Are
Performing And Can We Sustain It every year.
The City Leadership For Getting Is Where We're Act
Its Team effort I Know On That But Lets Take So Credit Because it is a team effort
I'm proud to be a part of the great team thats Doing Well and Our City is Growing
This Is What We All Came Not Here To Do It Its For Always To Make Change
In our city The Reason WhereIn And Possession's We're Ends Because we Wanted
See A Different So Then Were Seeing That Different Sucleur Everybody Who Supposed
Thank You for Coming & Getting To Let us Know this Stuff But Again
Bo, Take Over To you so Im Going Go To Jill
Grant Money So Im Going To Talk About Both The Minutes Are A Quick
This One Lets Talking about It Korean Think They Received $500 More Than
And Its Dispaded Which Is Great Free Money
We're asking You to Approve That so they Can Spend it
Second one is a second Insurance Recovery Check For the Joe Calling
Second Let You Get A Way That Is Your Got To Make Just Quarment
I make a Motion We Improve
Second
14 Enforcement of Public Authority Responsibility Between The Pure
Travelable Home and the City Mom, Regarding Inclusion
Certain city routes into travel transportation program
And I'm excited about This One.
We have email About It Thursday, Thanks The Exciting
So Been Are You Going To Take Up Here
What this Does Is the Pure Yetried is Asking Our Permission
to Add Some Of our City Streets There In Their Historic Reservation Founder
These Two They're Road Inden Torred
Which Means That Increases Emanent Federal Funding
The They Yet Which Stay In Term will Turn Back Over To Improvement Of Those
Roads in the City.
Charity Nation Has Done This For A Couple of Years
Or Us, this is First Time On The E-Sided The Liver
That One Of Our Tribes Is Going to Be Visited
But Hopefully Other Two Major tribes
Through Reservations Can Prize The Majority of The City of Myamo
Will Get The Hand And At Those Two Theiring Bendories
It Simply Helps Us Fund Renemations of Our Roads
There's a map for You to show you the Streets
I thought about.
We'll Be Enough Money That Is Going To Fix All Of These Streets
But One Time, but Hopefully Over time
They will Certainly Have A Significant Impact
Road Conditioner
Or BJ Tonal Art Heavy Traffic
That's One Time To Be Stosed
I'll Say it.
About 15 Memorendums Understanding
For The 2023 Autocounty Farmers Mark
Exhibs Here
We're Bring Four You Tonight
A Autocounony Cover Mark
There is Excellent Changes
Do Get the Chex Stuff Fixed Through This Year
But On Work Off, Sorry
Well, they're not going to ask them.
And then I came in yet as there was the county of Arpathons because you got a bit through
County has that problem?
The bid is out so it probably won't be done till summer
Probably like at least
They've gotta have fans and their little right
At Bathroom's air condition
What are your goals about him pull down
I know you've done that, but it will prove best.
All right 16 contract with Schneiders fireworks and importing company in the amount of $20
thousand for their event on 4th July 2023
I'm pretty sure city manager is doesn't need to sign contract
We went 15-to 20
That's not always going go 25 this year
This little bride
Can we amend it?
With the 25
Well, yeah I thought Scott and he said that Schinger Law
Because to give like 2000-hettos they're 22
So there were a second biggest fireworks show
That's what you think
How about if we better find out where will go into kiss money first
It is five
Is that no?
Oh, it's both from
I'll make a motion to approve the 20
17 member of understanding between city and my amount
Fairboard for use at fairgrounds show barn
For fiscal year 2324
Okay. Thanks
How about new business in many which is the residence of the post office agenda
19 staff reports
20 mayor or council community announcement
21 city manager communications
22 is mean when I'll be continued from the council chambers
Reconvening staff rooms, the purpose of executive session